Paul Goodman Papers
Paul Goodman Papers
1958-1967
Goodman, Paul, 1911-1972.
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, poet. Includes correspondence; articles, book manuscripts, a galley proof, poems; and published material, including articles and clippings (1963-1964).
149011
Biographical History
Paul Goodman (1911-1972) was an American author, poet, social critic and educator.
Goodman was born in New York City on September 9, 1911. After graduating from City College in New York, he received his Ph.D. in Humanities from the University of Chicago. Goodman taught at the University of Chicago, New York University, Black Mountain College, and Sarah Lawrence, and lectured widely at various universities throughout the country. He was associated with the New York and Cleveland institutes for Gestalt Therapy and the University Seminar on the Problems of Interpretation at Columbia. He is also a Fellow of the Institute for Policy Studies in Washington, DC.
Goodman wrote for Commentary, Politics, Kenyon Review, Resistance, Liberation, Partisan Review, Dissent, The Quarterly Review of Literature, The New Republic, Moviegoer, and the Village Voice. His fiction includes The Facts of Life, The Break-Up of Our Camp, Parent's Day, The Empire City, Making Do, and a volume of verse, The Lordly Hudson. He also wrote two books of criticism, Kafka's Prayer and The Structure of Literature. In the area of social studies, in addition to co-authoring Communitas and Gestalt Therapy, he wrote Art and Social Nature, Growing Up Absurd (the book for which he is best known), Utopian Essays and Practical Purposes, Drawing the Line, Community of Scholars, and Compulsory Mis-Education.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Paul Goodman Papers consist of correspondence/subject files, writings and memorabilia of the American author, poet and activist. Correspondence-subject files contain correspondence primarily from 1962-1965 including a selection of unfriendly letters to Mr. Goodman as well as minutes of a school board meeting. Writings includes manuscripts, typescripts, proofs and published versions of poetry, several articles and books. Memorabilia contains a calendar, newspaper clippings and an undateded test on Growing Up Absurd.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically for the most part.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Goodman, Paul, 1911-1972.; Anthony, Carl, 1932-; Breslin, Jimmy.; Hoggart, Richard, 1918-2014.; Holt, John Caldwell, 1923-1985.; Horn, Zoia.; Howe, Irving.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Konvitz, Milton R. (Milton Ridvas), 1908-2003.; Langness, L. L. (Lewis L.), 1929-; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Raskin, Marcus G.; Rosenberg, Harold, 1906-1978.; Schreiber, Daniel.; Sheehy Skeffington, Owen, 1909-1970.; Sofejko, Henry A.; Tannenbaum, Frank, 1893-1969.; Van Dresser, Peter, 1909-1983.; Ward, Colin C.; Wasserman, Saul; Authors, American.; Poets, American.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Poems.; Authors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Anarchy, See Ward, Colin.
  - Anthony, Carl, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Baldridge, Letitia, See Kennedy, John F..
  - Bashlow, Robert, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Board of Education of the City of New York, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Breslin, Jimmy, 1963 (Box 1)
  - College of the Virgin Islands, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Federal Communications Commission, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Harlem Education Project, See Anthony, Carl.
  - Harvard-Radcliffe Liberal Union, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Hoggart, Richard, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Holt, John Caldwell, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Horn, Zoia Markovna, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Howe, Irving, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1962 (Box 1)
  - Konvitz, Milton R., 1963 (Box 1)
  - Langness, L.L., 1963 (Box 1)
  - Lindsay, John V., 1963 (Box 1)
  - The Macmillan Company, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Morningside-121st Street-Amsterdam Tenants' Committee, 1964 (Box 1)
  - The New Republic, 1963 (Box 1)
  - New York City Local School Board Districts 6 and 8, 1962 (Box 1)
  - The New York Review of Books, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Newsweek, 1962 (Box 1)
  - The Northern Student Movement Coordinating Committee for Civil Rights, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Project: School Dropouts, See Schreiber, Daniel.
  - Raskin, Marcus G., 1963 (Box 1)
  - Rosenberg, Harold, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Schreiber, Daniel, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Sheehy-Skeffington, Owen, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Sofejko, Henry A., 1964 (Box 1)
  - Tannenbaum, Frank, 1963 (Box 1)
  - The University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 1963,1964 (Box 1)
  - Van Dresser, Peter, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Ward, Colin, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Wasserman, Saul, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous unfriendly, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1962-1964; undated (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Manuscripts, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Published, 1963, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Books
    - Like a Conquered Province, 1962 (Box 1)
      - Author's proofs with corrections (Box 1)
    - The Lordly Hudson
      - Typescript with corrections (Box 2)
    - People or Personnel (Box 2)
      - Author's proof (Box 2)
      - Proofs with corrections (Box 2)
      - Typescript with corrections (Box 2)
  - Poetry (Box 2)
  - Lectures, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Letters to editors, 1960, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes, 1961-1964, undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Calendar, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1963, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Test on Growing Up Absurd, undated (Box 2)